[Music]
foreign
lead poisoning still occurs in the
United States despite extensive
prevention efforts and strict
regulations
ayurvedic supplements for example
specifically marketed to pregnant women
exceeded safety Levels by up to 4
million percent making
ayurvedic medicine use and lead
poisoning a continued concern in the
United States
heavy metals are intentionally added to
the supplements
but don't worry ayurvedic practitioners
claim the lead has been detoxified with
cowpea
calcium supplements can be an additional
source of lead contamination something
we've known for about a half a century
now
calcium supplements made from bone may
have the highest lead levels but just
regular calcium supplements were found
contaminated too including a number of
big National brands
diet wise the greatest contributor to
lead intake of children and their
parents may be Dairy but the most
concentrated source
may be wild game shot with lead
containing ammunition
concerns have been raised by hunters
though that lead-free bullets wouldn't
have the same wounding capacity but CT
scans of kills show just as much damage
is inflicted
demonstrating that lead-free bullets
have equivalent killing Effectiveness
even against ballistic soap which
evidently has a similar density to vital
organs
workers and like battery plants can be
exposed to a lot of lead but the number
one non-occupational lead exposure is
shooting Firearms not eating lead-laden
meat just target practice in indoor
firing ranges 75 of Target Shooters have
elevated lead levels in their blood even
outside Airborne lead released by The
friction of the bullet against the
barrel or lead containing primers can
lead to substantial lead exposure both
in the people and in local Wildlife as
well as the soil with lead levels higher
than that found next to an industrial
Lead Factory
most lead in urban soil though is from
the Decades of lead paint and leaded
gasoline raising concerns about Urban
Gardens most of the lead doesn't get
taken up by the plants though but can
stick to the leaves and Roots this is
bad news and then even crops from raised
beds using clean soil may get
contaminated in an urban environment but
the good news is that the lead can
presumably just be washed off
the health benefits of gardening and
fresh produce would likely more than
compensate for the risk at most sites
eggs from backyard chickens however
should be tested for lead since the lead
gets inside the egg and so can't be
washed off most of the lead ends up in
the bird's skeleton though which raises
the question what happens when you try
to make chicken soup
there may be an upswing in people
boiling bones due to encouragement from
paleo diet advocates
the problem is that lead is a neurotoxin
and not just a neurotoxin it adversely
affects the bone marrow and digestive
tract and kidneys and circulatory system
and hormones and reproduction
symptoms of too much lead exposure
include impaired cognition anemia
abdominal pain kidney problems high
blood pressure miscarriages memory
problems constipation impotence
depression poor concentration
Etc
and we know from Human studies that lead
is sequestered in the bones
when there's a lot of lead turnover like
menopause or during pregnancy lead
levels in the blood can go up this bump
can be minimized during pregnancy by
getting enough calcium and lowering
sodium intake
when astronauts lose bone in Space the
lead is released into their bloodstream
but ironically since they're no longer
exposed to all the lead on Earth their
overall lead levels may go down
bones are so good at sucking up blood
they can be like sprinkled on firing
ranges to prevent lead from leaching
further into the environment
so these researchers were concerned that
the boiling of farm animal bones might
release lead into the broth
so they made three types of organic
chicken broth one with the bones one
with just the meat and one with the skin
and cartilage
all the soups exceeded the maximum
allowable dose level for lead even the
Boneless
surprisingly the skin in cartilage was
the worst exceeding the safety level per
one cup serving by like
475 percent
foreign